<Scene>
  <Khachkars>
  
  
    <Khachkar>
      <Id>1</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-11th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Bad/covered with mold and moss 
</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription></Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures> Khachkars are partially covered with mold and moss and it’s difficult to identify various details and ornaments. Khachkars were probably carved between the 9th and 11th centuries, as they have a simple design without various ornaments and forms. The first khachkar (from the left) has two crosses that have two wings with two triple-loops. Rosette is crowned with a ribbon-like border - resembling a shield or a tray and it is separated from the niche with relief cylinder. Khachkar has a separated cornice and the left and the rights parts probably represent geometric ornaments (probably, because it’s hard to identify because of mold and moss). Khachkar in the middle has represents a cross with two wings with two triple-loops. The two little crosses on the right and the left parts of the central cross, symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ. There are also two little crosses at the upper part of the main cross. The main cross also has a palm décor that originates from the bottom of the cross. This khachkar has a separated cornice with geometrical decorations and the right and the left parts represent various ornaments. The third khachkar (from the left) represents a cross that has two wings with two triple-loops. It has a simple palm décor and a separated cornice with geometrical decorations. The left and the right part also represent various ornaments.
</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
      <Khachkar>
  <Id>4</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-11th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good
</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription></Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loop is stretched and has a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The niche represents the ritualistic character of the cross to the believer (e.g. worshiping) and symbolizes the terrestrial sphere, and the abstract-universal measure of the cross (Petrosyan, H. 2008). The two little crosses on the right and the left parts of the central cross, symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ. There are two encircled two little flowers at the top of the two wings of the main cross. The palm decor is depicted as originating from the cross. Such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the cross as an all bearing tree (Petrosyan, H. 2008). The trimmings of the palm décor join the two little crosses. The cornice of the khachkar and the right and the left parts represent various geometrical and vegetative ornaments.

</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
      
	  
	  <Khachkar>
  <Id>6</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-12th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Bad/covered with mold and moss 
</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription></Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>"
Khachkar is partially covered with mold and moss and it’s difficult to identify various details and ornaments. The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loop is stretched and has a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The two little crosses on the right and the left parts of the central cross, symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ.  The niche represents the ritualistic character of the cross to the believer (e.g. worshiping) and symbolizes the terrestrial sphere, and the abstract-universal measure of the cross (Petrosyan, H. 2008).  Although it’s difficult to identify the details, it can be seen that the palm décor is depicted as originating from the cross and such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the cross as an all bearing tree (Petrosyan, H. 2008). The cornice of the khachkar and the right and the left parts represent various geometrical and vegetative ornaments.
</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  
    <Khachkar>
  <Id>7</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-12th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good/covered with mold and moss 
</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription></Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>
The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loop is stretched and has a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. Two pomegranates that originate from the upper part of the cross stimulate the Christian allegory of fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008). The palm décor is depicted as originating from the cross and such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the cross as an all bearing tree (Petrosyan, H. 2008). The cornice of the khachkar and the right and the left parts represent various geometrical and vegetative ornaments. There is a cross originating from the palm decor which probably has a form of the tree of life.
</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  
   <Khachkar>
  <Id>8</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-11th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good/covered with mold and moss 
</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription></Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures></ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  
  <Khachkar>
  <Id>9</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-12th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription> "Me ...(difficult to understand the name) carved this khachkar"</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>The cross is carved in a unique niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loop is stretched and has a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The niche represents the ritualistic character of the cross to the believer (e.g. worshiping) and symbolizes the terrestrial sphere, and the abstract-universal measure of the cross (Petrosyan, H. 2008). Two pomegranates are carved in the middle of the two triple- loops of the wings. The other pomegranate originates from the top of the niche. Pomegranates stimulate the Christian allegory of fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008). The two grape rods originate from the niche and represent Heavenly Garden. As Petrosyan (2008) notes, the depiction of fruits also is good evidence for the Armenian perception of the world as a garden, which formed at least as early as the Urartian period and, evidently, developed steadily throughout the whole Middle Ages. The palm décor is depicted as originating from the cross, and such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the cross as an all bearing tree (Petrosyan, H. 2008). Rosette is crowned with a ribbon-like border - resembling a shield or a tray. The right and the left parts of khachkar and the cornice have a very interesting combination of geometric ornaments that are all interlaced, and it seems that there is no beginning and no end. The infinity of the line visibly insures the semblance of eternity and completeness of the composition (Petrosyan, H. 2008).
</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  <Khachkar>
  <Id>10</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-12th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Bad/covered in mold and moss </CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription> </Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>Khchkar has 4 crosses each with two wings that have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the crosses. There are two little crosses in the middle of the big crosses. There is circle under the two big crosses probably representing the Armenian eternity sign (it’s hard to see because of the moss and mold). There are two pomegranates cared near the two triple- loops of the big crosses. Pomegranates stimulate the Christian allegory of fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008). The right and the left parts and some the cornice interlaced ornaments. There cornice represents three little crosses.

</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  <Khachkar>
  <Id>11</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-12th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>1th and 2th -Good, 3th and 4th-Bad (from left to right)</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription> </Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>All four khachkars have two wings that have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the crosses. There are two pomegranates beneath the wings of the khachkars and stimulate the Christian allegory of fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008). All khachkars have cornices that represent interlaced geometric ornaments. The second khachkar from the left has a unique interlaced niche. The palm decors of the 3rd and the 4th khachkars are barely seen because of the mold and moss. Those originate from the cross. Such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the cross as an all bearing tree (Petrosyan, H. 2008). The palm decors of the 1st and the 2nd khachkar also originate from the cross and transform into snakes that symbolize the defense of the garden-paradise (paradise-tree). The right and the left parts of the khachkars represent various geometric and vegetative ornaments.
</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  
  
  <Khachkar>
  <Id>17</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-12th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Bad/the cornice is partially broken </CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription> </Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loop is stretched and has a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The two little crosses on the right and the left parts of the central cross, symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ.  The niche represents the ritualistic character of the cross to the believer (e.g. worshiping) and symbolizes the terrestrial sphere, and the abstract-universal measure of the cross (Petrosyan, H. 2008).Two pomegranates that originate from the upper part of the cross stimulate the Christian allegory of fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008).The cornice of the khachkar is partially broken and there is a little cross carved on the right part. The right and the left parts of the cross represent various interlaced geometrical and vegetative ornaments. There are probably three little crosses carved under the main cross and their wings are capped with double buttons (typical to the 9-10th century khachkars).
</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  <Khachkar>
  <Id>18</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good/partially covered with mold and moss </CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription></Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The two little crosses on the right and the left parts of the central cross, symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ.  The niche represents the ritualistic character of the cross to the believer (e.g. worshiping) and symbolizes the terrestrial sphere, and the abstract-universal measure of the cross (Petrosyan, H. 2008).Two pomegranates that originate from the upper part of the cross stimulate the Christian allegory of fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008). The palm decor is depicted as originating from the cross. Such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the cross as an all bearing tree (Petrosyan, H. 2008). The trimmings of the palm décor join the two little crosses. The cornice and the right and the left parts of khachkar represent geometric ornaments. The upper part of the cornice represents nine decors representing niches.
</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  
  <Khachkar>
  <Id>19</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good/partially covered with mold and moss </CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription> </Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>Khachkar from the left has two wings with two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The palm decor is depicted as originating from the cross. It has a simple design. There are three little crosses and an early model of a rosette under the palm décor. The cornice represents a cross with wings are capped with double buttons (typical to the 9-10th-century khachkars).The right and the left parts of khachkar and cornice represent interlaced geometric ornaments.The second khachkar is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The right and the left parts represent interlaced geometric ornaments and three chamomiles on each side. There are two interlaced crosses under the central cross. The cornice represents geometrical ornaments.

</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  
  <Khachkar>
  <Id>21</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-12th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Bad/the cornice is partially broken </CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription> </Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The palm decors originates from the cross and transforms into snakes that symbolize the defense of the garden-paradise (paradise-tree). The right and the left parts of the khachkars represent various geometric and vegetative ornaments. There are probably pomegranate leaves originating from the niche. Those stimulate the Christian allegory of fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008).The cornice represents interlaced geometric ornaments.
</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  <Khachkar>
  <Id>22</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Bad
</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription> </Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>The main cross has two wings with two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The palm decor originates from the cross and transforms into snakes that symbolize the defense of the garden-paradise (paradise-tree). The right and the left parts of the khachkars represent various geometric and vegetative ornaments. Two pomegranates that originate from the upper part of the cross stimulate the Christian allegory of fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008). Rosette is crowned with a ribbon-like border - resembling a shield or a tray. The cornice represents interlaced geometric ornaments.

</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
   <Khachkar>
  <Id>23</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good
</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription> Difficult to read because of mold and moss
</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The palm decor originates from the cross and such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the cross as an all bearing tree (Petrosyan, H. 2008). It transforms into snakes that symbolize the defense of the garden-paradise (paradise-tree). The edges of the palm décor transform into birds that link to the palm tree as the tree of life. The right and the left parts of the khachkars represent various interlaced geometric and vegetative ornaments. The cornice has a domelike appearance and represents interlaced geometric ornaments.There is also a little cross under the palm decor.
</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  
  
   <Khachkar>
  <Id>24</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Bad/covered in moss and mold 
</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription> 
</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The palm decor originates from the cross and such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the cross as an all bearing tree (Petrosyan, H. 2008). It transforms into snakes that symbolize the defense of the garden-paradise (paradise-tree). And the edges of palm décor transform into birds that link to the palm tree as the tree of life. The right and the left parts of the khachkars represent various interlaced geometric and vegetative ornaments. The cornice has a domelike appearance and represents interlaced geometric ornaments.
</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  
  <Khachkar>
  <Id>25</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Bad/covered in mold and moss
</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription> 
</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The right and the left parts of the khachkars represent various geometric and vegetative ornaments. Two pomegranates that originate from the upper part of the cross stimulate the Christian allegory of fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008). Khachkar has a beautiful rosette that has vegetative and geometric ornaments. The right and the left parts of rosette represent two little crosses. Rosette is crowned with a ribbon-like border - resembling a shield or a tray.The palm decor originates from the cross and such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the cross as an all bearing tree (Petrosyan, H. 2008). It’s difficult to identify the form of the trimmings of the palm décor because of mold and moss. It can be barely seen that those transform into two little pomegranates.
</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  
  <Khachkar>
  <Id>26</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good
</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription> 
</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>Khachkar represents two crosses. The two wings of each khachkar have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the crosses. The right and the left parts of the khachkar represent various geometric and vegetative ornaments. Khachkar has a beautiful rosette that has a form of a chamomile with 12 petals that symbolize 12 apostles. The cornice represents interlaced geometric ornaments. Palm decors originate from the crosses and such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the crosses as all bearing trees (Petrosyan, H. 2008).
</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  
  <Khachkar>
  <Id>27</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-14th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Bad/the upper part is broken

</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription> 
</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>Khachkar represents two crosses. The two wings of each khachkar have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the crosses. The right and the left parts of the khachkar represent various geometric and vegetative ornaments. Palm decors originate from the crosses and such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the crosses as all bearing trees (Petrosyan, H. 2008). The edges of palm décor transform into birds that link to the palm tree as the tree of life.
</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  <Khachkar>
  <Id>29</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-14th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription> 
</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The right and the left parts of the khachkars represent various geometric and vegetative ornaments. Three pomegranates that originate from the upper part of the cross stimulate the Christian allegory of fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008). The cornice represents 5 niches each with a vegetative ornament. The palm decor originates from the cross and such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the cross as an all bearing tree (Petrosyan, H. 2008). It transforms into snakes that symbolize the defense of the garden-paradise (paradise-tree).
</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  
  <Khachkar>
  <Id>30</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription> 
</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The right and the left parts of the khachkar represent interlaced geometric ornaments. The palm decor originates from the cross and such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the cross as an all bearing tree (Petrosyan, H. 2008). It transforms into birds that link to the palm tree as the tree of life. Khackar doesn’t have a cornice, it has two little crosses at the top right and left parts of the main cross.
</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  
  <Khachkar>
  <Id>31</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good but covered in mold and moss</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription> Difficult to read because of mold and moss
</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>Khachar from the left represents a cross carved in a niche. The two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The niche represents the ritualistic character of the cross to the believer (e.g. worshiping) and symbolizes the terrestrial sphere, and the abstract-universal measure of the cross (Petrosyan, H. 2008).The right and the left parts of the khachkars represent various geometric and vegetative ornaments including flowers and crosses. The two little crosses on the right and the left parts of the central cross, symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ. The cornice represents 5 niches each with a cross. The palm decor originates from the cross and such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the cross as an all bearing tree (Petrosyan, H. 2008). It transforms into snakes that symbolize the defense of the garden-paradise (paradise-tree). The bottom of khachkar represents for separate crosses. Khachkar on the right is covered in mold and moss and it’s difficult to identify various details. The cross is carved in a niche and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The cornice probably represents various little crosses. Khachkar doesn’t have a palm décor .Instead of a palm décor, there are two crosses at the right and the left parts under the main cross that symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ. The right and the left parts represent interlaced geometric ornaments. The bottom of khachkar represents for separate crosses.

</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  
  <Khachkar>
  <Id>45</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural objects on two big pedestals in Noradu cemetery</Scenario>
      
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good but covered in mold and moss</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription> Difficult to read because of mold and moss
</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>Khachkar on the left is covered in mold and moss and it’s difficult to identify various details. The cross has two wings that have two triple- loops and the middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The right and the left parts of the khachkar represent interlaced geometric ornaments. The two little crosses on the right and the left parts of the central cross, symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ. The cross of the khachkar on the right is carved in a niche and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The cornice represents three crosses middle. There are two crosses on the right and the left parts of the main cross that symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ. The right and the left parts represent combinations of geometric ornaments and crosses. The palm decor originates from the cross and such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the cross as an all bearing tree (Petrosyan, H. 2008). It transforms into birds that link to the palm tree as the tree of life.
</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
  </Khachkar>
  
  </Khachkars>
</Scene>