<Scene>
  <Khachkars>
    <Khachkar>
      <Id>24</Id>
      <Location>Amaghu Valley, Vayodz Dzor Province, Armenia</Location>
      <LatLong>39.684061°N 45.232872°E</LatLong>
      <Scenario>Scenario: Freestanding sculptural object at Noravank Monastery Complex</Scenario>
      <Setting>Setting: Narrow gorge</Setting>
      <Landscape>Landscape: Moutain</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Accessibility: Difficult</Accessibility>
      <Category>Category: Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Production Period: Probably 12th or 13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Normal</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription>Inscription: Difficult to understand</Inscription>
      <Motive>No data</Motive>
      <ImportantFeatures>
        The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loop is stretched and has a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The two little crosses on the right and the left parts of the central cross, symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ. Two pomegranates, carved beneath the two wings stimulate the Christian allegory of fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008). Rosette is carved within a beautifully decorated circle with lace details. It represents two icons, but because of the bad condition, it’s hard to understand who the characters might be. Khachkar has a unique palm décor. It is situated on the rosette, and it appears in the form of birds who carry the central cross. The right and the left sides of the stone represent vertically located decorations. From the bottom of the stone, beneath the inscription, the decorations represent six chamomiles within a flower composed from tiny ornaments. And the flower is within a rhombus. There is also an iconography in the middle of the cornice, but again, because of the bad condition, it’s hard to identify the character. The right and the left parts of the cornice that are carved in relief like lace represent compositions of various vegetative ornaments.
      </ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
    </Khachkar>
  </Khachkars>
</Scene>