<Scene>
  <Khachkars>
    <Khachkar>
      <Id>16</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <LatLong>40°22′48″N 45°10′48″E</LatLong>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural object on a pedestal in Noradus cemetery</Scenario>
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <MastersName>Unknown</MastersName>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <Motive>As gravestone</Motive>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good but covered in mold an moss</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription>Difficult to understand</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>Khachkar on the left is covered in mold and moss and it’s difficult to identify various details. The cross has two wings that have two triple- loops and the middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The right and the left parts of the khachkar represent interlaced geometric ornaments. The two little crosses on the right and the left parts of the central cross, symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ. The cross of the khachkar on the right is carved in a niche and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The cornice represents three crosses middle. There are two crosses on the right and the left parts of the main cross that symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ. The right and the left parts represent combinations of geometric ornaments and crosses. The palm decor originates from the cross and such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the cross as an all bearing tree (Petrosyan, H. 2008). It transforms into birds that link to the palm tree as the tree of life</ImportantFeatures>
      <BackSide></BackSide>
      <HistoryOwnership></HistoryOwnership>
      <CommemorativeActivities></CommemorativeActivities>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www.khachkar.am</Referances>
    </Khachkar>
  </Khachkars>
</Scene>