<Scene>
  <Khachkars>
    <Khachkar>
      <Id>38</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <LatLong>40°22′48″N 45°10′48″E</LatLong>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural object on a pedestal in Noradus cemetery</Scenario>
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <MastersName>Unknown</MastersName>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately  10-12th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <Motive>Khachkar is a gravestone</Motive>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription> "Me ... (difficult to understand the name) carved this khachkar"</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>The cross is carved in a unique niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loop is stretched and has a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The niche represents the ritualistic character of the cross to the believer (e.g. worshiping) and symbolizes the terrestrial sphere, and the abstract-universal measure of the cross (Petrosyan, H. 2008). Two pomegranates are carved in the middle of the two triple- loops of the wings. The other pomegranate originates from the top of the niche. Pomegranates stimulate the Christian allegory of fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008). The two grape rods originate from the niche and represent Heavenly Garden. As Petrosyan (2008) notes, the depiction of fruits also is good evidence for the Armenian perception of the world as a garden, which formed at least as early as the Urartian period and, evidently, developed steadily throughout the whole Middle Ages. The palm décor is depicted as originating from the cross, and such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the cross as an all bearing tree (Petrosyan, H. 2008). Rosette is crowned with a ribbon-like border - resembling a shield or a tray. The right and the left parts of khachkar and the cornice have a very interesting combination of geometric ornaments that are all interlaced, and it seems that there is no beginning and no end. The infinity of the line visibly insures the semblance of eternity and completeness of the composition (Petrosyan, H. 2008)</ImportantFeatures>
      <BackSide></BackSide>
      <HistoryOwnership></HistoryOwnership>
      <CommemorativeActivities></CommemorativeActivities>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www.khachkar.am</Referances>
    </Khachkar>
  </Khachkars>
</Scene>