<Scene>
  <Khachkars>
    <Khachkar>
      <Id>34</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <LatLong>40°22′48″N 45°10′48″E</LatLong>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural object on a pedestal in Noradus cemetery</Scenario>
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal</Accessibility>
      <MastersName>Unknown</MastersName>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately 11-13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <Motive>Khachkar is a gravestone</Motive>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good, partially covered with mold and moss</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription></Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The two little crosses on the right and the left parts of the central cross, symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ.  The niche represents the ritualistic character of the cross to the believer (e.g. worshiping) and symbolizes the terrestrial sphere, and the abstract-universal measure of the cross (Petrosyan, H. 2008).Two pomegranates that originate from the upper part of the cross stimulate the Christian allegory of fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008). The palm decor is depicted as originating from the cross. Such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the cross as an all bearing tree (Petrosyan, H. 2008). The trimmings of the palm décor join the two little crosses. The cornice and the right and the left parts of khachkar represent geometric ornaments. The upper part of the cornice represents nine decors representing niches</ImportantFeatures>
      <BackSide></BackSide>
      <HistoryOwnership></HistoryOwnership>
      <CommemorativeActivities></CommemorativeActivities>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www.khachkar.am</Referances>
    </Khachkar>
  </Khachkars>
</Scene>