<Scene>
  <Khachkars>
    <Khachkar>
      <Id>1</Id>
      <Location>Noratus historical village, Gegharkunik Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding sculptural object on a pedestal in Noradus cemetery</Scenario>
      <Setting>Medieval cemetery</Setting>
      <Landscape>Flat land</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Normal </Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Approximately 11-13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good but covered in mold an moss</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription>None</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>The cross of the khachkar from the left is carved in a niche and has two wings that have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The right and the left parts of the khachkar represent interlaced geometric ornaments. The two little crosses on the right and the left parts of the central cross, symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ. The cornice represents a cross and interlaced geometric ornaments. Rosette is crowned with a ribbon-like border - resembling a shield or a tray and it is separated from the niche with relief cylinder. The cross of the khachkar on the right is carved in a niche and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loops are stretched and have a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The cornice represents a cross in the middle and geometric ornaments on the right and the left parts. Khachkar doesn’t have a palm décor Instead of a palm décor, there are two crosses on the right and the left parts of the main cross that symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ. The right and the left parts represent combinations of geometric ornaments and crosses. The bottom of khachkar represents 4 separate sections with crosses and interlaced ornaments.</ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
    </Khachkar>
  </Khachkars>
</Scene>