<Scene>
  <Khachkars>
    <Khachkar>
      <Id>1</Id>
      <Location>Amaghu Valley, Vayodz Dzor Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding, sculptural object at Etchmiadzin Cathedral complex</Scenario>

      <Setting>Narrow gorge</Setting>
      <Landscape>Moutain</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Difficult</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Bad: the upper part/the cornice of the khachkar and the bottom right part are partially broken.</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription>One part of the text is missing because of the broken </Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>
        The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loop is stretched and has a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The two little crosses on the right and the left parts of the central cross, symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ. Two pomegranates, carved beneath the two wings stimulate the Christian allegory of fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008). Another interesting component of khachkar is the rosette which might be a modifed version of Armenian eternity sign. Rosette is carved within a beautifully decorated circle with vegetative ornaments (mainly palm leaves). The palm décor under the central cross is situated on the rosette, and it appears in the form of snakes. The snakes surround the two parts of the main cross symbolizing symbolizes the defense of the garden-paradise (paradise-tree) (Petrosyan H, 2008). The right and the left sides of the stone represent vertically located decorations. From the bottom of the stone, beneath the inscription, the decorations represent five flowers within a foursquare which are connected with the relief line, foursquare with a swastika and a lace ornaments on both right and left sides. The infinity of the relief line visibly ensures the semblance of eternity and completeness of the composition (Petrosyan H. 2008).
      </ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
    </Khachkar>
    <Khachkar>
      <Id>2</Id>
      <Location>Amaghu Valley, Vayodz Dzor Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding, sculptural object at Etchmiadzin Cathedral complex</Scenario>

      <Setting>Narrow gorge</Setting>
      <Landscape>Moutain</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Difficult</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Probably 13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Normal</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription>One part of the text is missing because of the broken </Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>
        The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loop is stretched and has a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The two little crosses on the right and the left parts of the central cross, symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ. On the right and the left sides of the main cross, as well in the corners of the niche, the artist carved angles. The details of the little crosses are carved like  braid, and the wings are capped with double buttons. Khachkar’s cornice represents a Christ in the middle, surrounded by animals. The upper part of the cornice contains inscription, and the right and the left parts represent intertwined ornaments. Khachkar has a unique rosette; it’s a beautifully decorated circle with the same ornaments of the cornice, with the head of Adam in the middle which symbolizes Goghota. Rosette has a salience and is crowned with a ribbon-like border - resembling a shield or a tray. It separated from the niche with relief cylinder. The right and the left sides of the stone represent vertically located decorations. From the bottom of the stone, the decorations represent five eight-sided polygons with the same ornaments on both right and left sides. Khachkar also contains two figurative reliefs beneath the inscription which represent half animal half human creatures.
      </ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
    </Khachkar>

    <Khachkar>
      <Id>3</Id>
      <Location>Amaghu Valley, Vayodz Dzor Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding, sculptural object at Etchmiadzin Cathedral complex</Scenario>
      <Setting>Narrow gorge</Setting>
      <Landscape>Moutain</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Difficult</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Probably 12th or 13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Normal</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription>Difficult to understand</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>
        The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loop is stretched and has a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The two little crosses on the right and the left parts of the central cross, symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ. Two pomegranates, carved beneath the two wings stimulate the Christian allegory of fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008). Rosette is carved within a beautifully decorated circle with lace details. It represents two icons, but because of the bad condition, it’s hard to understand who the characters might be. Khachkar has a unique palm décor. It is situated on the rosette, and it appears in the form of birds who carry the central cross. The right and the left sides of the stone represent vertically located decorations. From the bottom of the stone, beneath the inscription, the decorations represent six chamomiles within a flower composed from tiny ornaments. And the flower is within a rhombus. There is also an iconography in the middle of the cornice, but again, because of the bad condition, it’s hard to identify the character. The right and the left parts of the cornice that are carved in relief like lace represent compositions of various vegetative ornaments.

      </ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
    </Khachkar>
    <Khachkar>
      <Id>5</Id>
      <Location>Amaghu Valley, Vayodz Dzor Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding, sculptural object at Etchmiadzin Cathedral complex</Scenario>
      <Setting>Narrow gorge</Setting>
      <Landscape>Moutain</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Difficult</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Probably 11th or 12th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription>No inscription</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>
        The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loop is stretched and has a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross.Khachkar does not have a rosette. It has a palm décor which is depicted as originating from the cross. Such a perception corresponds to the Christian notions of the cross as an all bearing tree (Petrosyan H, 2008). The right and the left sides of the stone, along with the bottom represent various ornaments which are like a woven thread. The cornice of khachkar represents six horizontally located flowers, inside intertwined circles.

      </ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
    </Khachkar>
	
	
	<Khachkar>
      <Id>7</Id>
      <Location>Amaghu Valley, Vayodz Dzor Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding, sculptural object at Etchmiadzin Cathedral complex</Scenario>
      <Setting>Narrow gorge</Setting>
      <Landscape>Moutain</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Difficult</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>12th or 13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Good</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription>"Me, Sarkis carved this khachkar in rememberance of my brother Grigor"</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>
       The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loop is stretched and has a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. Two pomegranates, carved beneath the two wings stimulate the Christian allegory of fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008). Rosette has various vegetative ornaments (mainly palm leaves) and is crowned with a thin ribbon-like border - resembling a shield or a tray. The main cross is surrounded by rich vegetative decorations such as the grape and leaves of grape. In this khachkar, the palm decors appear on the right and left sides, from the bottom to the foursquare with swastikas and other ornaments. The cornice represents a pattern of intertwined elements.
      </ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
    </Khachkar>
	
	
	<Khachkar>
      <Id>8</Id>
      <Location>Amaghu Valley, Vayodz Dzor Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding, sculptural object at Etchmiadzin Cathedral complex</Scenario>
      <Setting>Narrow gorge</Setting>
      <Landscape>Moutain</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Difficult</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Probably 13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Bad</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription>Impossible to read</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>
      The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loop is stretched and has a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The two little crosses on the right and the left parts of the central cross, symbolize the two bandits crucified with the Christ. Two vegetative decorations that are carved beneath the two wings and transform into flowers of a pomegranate tree stimulating the Christian allegory of pomegranate fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008). Rosette is crowned with a ribbon-like border - resembling a shield or a tray and it is separated from the niche with relief cylinder. The palm décor under the central cross is situated on the rosette, and it appears in the form of snakes. The snakes surround the two parts of the main cross symbolizing symbolizes the defense of the garden-paradise (paradise-tree) (Petrosyan H, 2008). The right and the left sides of the stone represent vertically located decorations. From the bottom of the stone, beneath the inscription, the decorations represent nine chamomiles within a foursquare, which are connected with the relief line. From the upper part, between the third and the fourth chamomile decors, there is a decoration of swastika. Khachkar also has a cornice with decorations like is a woven thread.
      </ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
    </Khachkar>
	
	<Khachkar>
      <Id>9</Id>
      <Location>Amaghu Valley, Vayodz Dzor Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding, sculptural object at Etchmiadzin Cathedral complex</Scenario>
      <Setting>Narrow gorge</Setting>
      <Landscape>Moutain</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Difficult</Accessibility>
      <Category>Lace work</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>21th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Very good</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription>"Mercy the ones who had built the church, the ones who are thankful, the philanthropists, the Church servants and the others who died under the patronage of the Holy Church. 
 In memory of the philanthropists from Noravan-Tigran and Diana Hajetea</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>
     Khackhar is a variation of Momik's 14th century khachkar.The cross is carved in a niche, and the two wings have two triple- loops. The middle loop is stretched and has a form of a flower bud that gives a blossoming and vegetative appearance to the cross. The palm décor which is depicted as originating from the cross adorns the cross from all the sides. Near the bottom of the main cross it receives a form of leaves, under the wings of the cross it transforms into two pomegranates that stimulate the Christian allegory of fruits: under the sour rind, there are sweet seeds (Petrosyan, H.2008). The form of leaves also appears beneath the wings and under the niche. Rosette has a salience and its ornaments create a hole in the middle. The cornice of khachkar represents an iconography of God, surrounded by the Christ, animals and an eager. Rosette is carved within a beautifully decorated circle with vegetative ornaments (mainly palm leaves). The palm décor under the central cross is situated on the rosette, and it appears in the form of snakes. The snakes surround the two parts of the cross  symbolize the defense of the garden-paradise (paradise-tree) (Petrosyan H, 2008). The upper part of the niche represents two twin birds facing one another, pecking the grape rods and bushes), which depicts the celestial holy sphere, celestial garden, the immortality of souls, which can be reached through the mediation of the cross (Petrosyan, H. 2008).The right and the left sides of the stone represent vertically located eight-sided polygons filled with the lace ornaments.

      </ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
    </Khachkar>
	
	<Khachkar>
      <Id>11</Id>
      <Location>Amaghu Valley, Vayodz Dzor Province, Armenia</Location>
      <Scenario>Freestanding, sculptural object at Etchmiadzin Cathedral complex</Scenario>
      <Setting>Narrow gorge</Setting>
      <Landscape>Moutain</Landscape>
      <Accessibility>Difficult</Accessibility>
      <Category>Standart</Category>
      <ProductionPeriod>Probably 13th century</ProductionPeriod>
      <CoonditionOfPreservation>Very bad</CoonditionOfPreservation>
      <Inscription>Impossible to read</Inscription>
      <ImportantFeatures>
      Khachkar is in bad condition, and if we look on the bottom line of the main cross, we can assure that the two wings of the cross had two triple- loops. Rosette has a form of a flower, which has various palm decorations inside. There are also palm leaves originating from the bottom part of the rosette. The right and the left sides have various geometric ornaments.
      </ImportantFeatures>
      <Referances>Hamlet Petrosyan, www,khachkar.am</Referances>
    </Khachkar>
	
	
  </Khachkars>
</Scene>